Archdiocese of Dubuque Collection
University of Notre Dame Archives
Archdiocese of Dubuque Collection
1832-1950.
ADU
Catholic Church. Archdiocese of Dubuque (Iowa)
1 linear inch.
University of Notre Dame Archives Notre Dame, Indiana 46556
Scope and Content
Letters sent by Bishops Loras and Hennessy; manuscripts of lectures by Bishop Loras; drawings of saints for the Dubuque Cathedral; and a Denkschrift of Adam Handl, Richmond (Washington County), Iowa, 1861.
Background
The Diocese of Dubuque was erected in 1837 with Jean Mathias Peter Loras as first bishop, succeeded by T. Clement Smyth in 1857 and John Hennessy in 1866.
Catholic Church. Archdiocese of Dubuque (Iowa).; Loras, John Mathias Peter, 1792-1858.; Hennessy, John, 1825-1900.; Handl, Adam.; Catholic Church -- Iowa -- Dubuque.; Catholic Church -- Bishops -- Correspondence.; Letters.
Related Material
Leopoldinen-Stiftung im Kaisertume Osterreich Records
Ludwigs-Verein Records
Society for the Propagation of the Faith Records
Catholic Church. Congregatio de Propaganda Fide Records
Center for the Study of Religious Life Records
- Archdiocese of Dubuque: Manuscripts, CADU
  - Bishop Pierre Jean Mathias Loras, CADU /1
    - Letter to Fr. Edward Sorin from Bishop Pierre Jean Mathias Loras, 1844/1111; CADU /1a
    - Letter ("Dear Sir") from Bishop Pierre Jean Mathias Loras, 1853/0203; CADU /1b
    - Bishop Loras: notes on temptations, 1855; CADU /1c
    - Bishop Loras: notes on perseverance, 1839?; CADU /1d; All but the title "on perseverance" is in French
    - Written description of Bishop Loras, CADU /1e; "Tall - about six feet, blue? eyes, brown hair, fair complexion"
    - Bishop Loras: 6th lecture, on religious persecutions, 1846/11; CADU /1f
    - Bishop Loras: notes on priesthood, 1840/1120; CADU /1g
    - Bishop Loras: notes on the care to be taken of youth, 1842; CADU /1h
    - Bishop Loras: notes on motives of conversion, 1839; CADU /1i
    - Bishop Loras: notes on education of children, 1837/08; CADU /1j; On the same paper: sermon for the Feast of St Raphael, 1844, recommending that we pray to angels, and speaking of his affection for the Irish.
    - Bishop Loras: notes - Service de Dieu pendant la jeunesse (in French), 1832; CADU /1j
    - Bishop Loras: notes - Sur le Baptisme (in French), 1834; CADU /1k
    - Bishop Loras: notes on the Christian Priesthood, 1846; CADU /1l
    - Notes regarding the history of Saint Raphael Cathedral in Dubuque, 1839-1858; CADU /1m; Bishop Loras installed, cornerstone laid, etc. 7 notes, probably all written at the same time.
    - Bishop Loras: manuscript lectures (30 pages), 1843; CADU /1n
    - Churching Women (liturgy), CADU /1o
  - Denkschrift, 1851; CADU /2; "For the most revered and noble fathers in the provincial concilium to Cincinnati and for the holy apostolic throne in Rome.... As soon as a provincial consilium will take place in Cincinnati, the obedient will ask him to listen with the following points most highly acclaimed." Richmond, Washington County, Iowa, 24 April 1861, by Adam Handl, Katholischer Schullehrer [Catholic schoolteacher]. It includes the original manuscript, a 1950s handwritten transcription, and a typed transcription, all in German. The 1950s handwritten transcription was done on the back of history syllabi, including Notre Dame summer school.
  - Three letters from Bishop John Hennessy, 1885-1886; CADU /3
  - Letter to James F. Edwards from M. Barry, 1903/0924; CADU /4; saying that he has included some circulars, etc., issued by Archbishop John Keane [not enclosed]
  - Luigi Gregori drawings for Saint Raphael Cathedral in Dubuque, c1886; CADU /5
    12 drawings on 11 sheets: Saints Paul?, Dominic, Leo (Pope Leo I), Vincent de Paul, Jerome, Ambrose, Patrick, Francis of Assisi, Bernard (2), Thomas Aquinas, and John Chrysostom. Identifications are in Italian; what we think is St. Paul is not identified and has a bit different look to it than the others.
    In four issues of Volume 20, the Notre Dame Scholastic notes that Gregori was working on the Cathedral in 1886: Issue 4, Issue 8, Issue 11, and Issue 13.
    Issue 16 mentions Gregori's donation of 21 sketches to the Bishops Memorial Hall at Notre Dame in December 1886. A dozen of these sketches came to the archives. Notre Dame's Snite Museum of Art holds other sketches by Gregori for the cathedral in Dubuque.